this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
all right let's review a little bit now
I am not going to be consistent about my
choice of the speed of light sometimes I
will put it in and call it C other times
I will just call it one I will try to
tell you when when I do and I don't it's
just formulas get uh too complicated
when you put the C's in and you all
should be able to figure out if I give
you a formula in which the speed of
light is equal to one you should be able
to figure out by dimensional analysis
where the speeds of light where the
little C's
go uh but I'll here and there I'll
sprinkle in the C's and I'll sprinkle
them in when it's important when I think
that it's relevant and interesting to uh
to do so otherwise I will choose the
speed of light to be one which means we
work in units like light years per year
or light seconds per second
or uh or such such units all right so
let me review quickly let me just start
with Galilean
relativity the Galilean pre-
Einstein Newton Galileo relationship
ship between reference frames moving and
stationary reference frames is given by
the simple equations which are called
Galilean relativity or gilean
Transformations uh for example for
motion along a one-dimensional
line a uh the relationship between the
coordin it's in a moving Railroad train
and the stationary station r
x Prime is equal to x minus the velocity
of the train time T and T
Prime is equal to T time is the same for
everybody and the difference between x
coordinates is just there because the
move the origin of the moving frame is
moving with velocity V relative to the
stationary frame to draw a picture let
me just draw a picture of what these
Transformations look like if this is is
I'll think of myself as the moving train
and I'll think of you as the
stationary
um uh observers at rest so when I speak
of me that's moving when I speak of you
that's at rest of course I think I'm at
rest and I think you're moving and
that's of course what relativity is all
about but let's uh look at Galilean
relativity
first Gan relativity if I were to plot
the time axis
and the x axis and then on the same
graph draw the T Prime axis the T Prime
axis which stands for the location the
locus of points of the
origin of coordinates for the prime
moving Observer it would look at an
angle like so and the slope of that
angle or that angle would be controlled
by the velocity of the moving reference
frame it would be that line would be
given by X well it's just given by xal
VT which is the same as X Prime equal Z
so that's so much for how the moving
frame moves but then if I were to plot
the lines of constant time as seen in
the prime reference frame they're
exactly the same as the lines of
constant time in the unprimed reference
frame and so they look like that
you don't have to draw two axes for
for for space but you do have to draw
the T AIS and this would become the T
Prime
axis uh for the moving reference frame
for the moving coordinates so if we
manage if we made a
grid this would be the grid for the
moving Observer and the grid for the
stationary Observer would be similar
except the lines would be vertical
these are the basic equations that
govern the relationship between
observers in uh uh in Galilean
relativity notice that if you solve if
you invert the equations they simply
look like this they look like x = x
prime plus v t but I can also write that
as VT Prime since T and T Prime are the
same thing and T T is equal to T
Prime the relationship between the
primed and unprimed
coordinates is exactly the same as the
relationship the inverted relation
between the unprimed and the primed
coordinates with one exception you
change the sign of the Velocity that
just represents the fact that if you see
me moving down the track with velocity
plus v i see you moving backward in the
opposite direction with velocity minus V
so
that's how Galileo if he would have
written the equations would have thought
about relativity it is the way Newton
thought about it and it's the way
everybody else did until uh the Advent
of
uh the discovery that the speed of light
is the same in every reference frame
those equations are not consistent with
the speed of light being the same in
every reference frame they have to be
corrected and the last time we worked
out
what the rules about light imply about
the corrections to those equations up
there so let me write them down for you
to remind you they are of course the
Loren
Transformations and they look like X
Prime is equal to x minus VT exactly
as Newton and Galileo might have written
it but then there's a square root of 1
minus v^ s
downstairs now that's if you want to put
put back the speed of light put C equals
sometimes if you want to put back the
speed of light this equation doesn't
make good dimensional sense so velocity
has units of length per unit time you
want and a one has no units at all so
what you really want to do is divide
this by the speed of light squared v^2
over c^2 and of course if the velocity
of the moving reference frame the train
in this case is ordinary velocities 50 m
an hour 100 Mil an hour 1,000 mil an
hour even a million miles an
hour that's quite small by comparison
with the speed of light and v^2 over c^2
is very negligible even for a million
miles an hour uh v^2 over c^ s is a very
small number and so for most practical
purposes terrestrial physics physics not
involving um things moving with anywhere
as near the speed of light
this just becomes the same as
galileon sare Ro of one is one it's
exactly the same as galileon what about
t Prime now that was the new thing this
was the really new thing that t Prime
isn't just equal to T in other words
that time is not as universal as Newton
had thought Newton had believed in a
universal time God's time he I don't
think he called it that but uh we could
call it that
that everybody has exactly the same
timekeeping and therefore T Prime is
equal to T well that was exactly what
was
wrong um with Galilean relativity that
made it inconsistent with the rules that
the speed of light is the same in every
reference frame to correct it Einstein
wrote it that way T then
minus
VX divided by that same square root of 1
- v^2 over c^2 but this is also not
dimensionally correct to get it to be
dimensionally correct you have to
write velocity divided c^
2 time
x again if the velocity is small by
comparison with the speed of light so
that V over C is a very small number
then you can
ignore this term and you can ignore the
V2 over c^2 in the denominator and it
just reproduces t = t Prime all right
but this is the correct uh formula and
it differs significantly from the
galileon formula when the velocities get
up near the speed of light in fact when
the velocity gets to the speed of light
something crazy happens here because V
equal
c v / C is equal to 1 1 - 1 is 0
and you're asked to divide by zero
that's not a good
thing uh mathematically inconsistent and
so what it tells you is that a frame of
reference can never quite be moving with
a speed of light relative to another one
but when it starts to get close to the
speed of light we start to see
significant deviations from Newton and
Galileo now you might ask what about X
and Y there are two other coordinates of
space besides X sorry what about y and Z
I didn't mean X and Y what about Y and Z
the two other components if we're moving
down the train track then there's the
coordinate of space along the track but
there's also the coordinates of space
perpendicular to the
track those are Y and Z and the Loren
Transformations for them are very very
simple they are simply that y Prime is
the same as Y and Z Prime is the same as
Z in other words coordinates along the
direction of
motion get mixed up with the time in
this complicated way but the coordinates
perpendicular to the motion they are the
same for both frames of reference now if
you want to know why just imagine having
a meter stick moving on the train and a
meter stick standing still and the meter
sticks past each other like so
now do an observer and they pass each
other and they just touch an instant of
time and the question is whether the
ends of the meter sticks are at the same
place if they're at exactly the same
place then the two meter sticks will
look the same to every Observer all
right the question is will they actually
pass each other now the argument that
says that they will stay exactly the
same size goes like this imagine
yourself in a reference frame halfway
between the moving train and the
stationary train I'm sorry the
stationary station when halfway means an
observer moving along who sees me moving
with a velocity and sees you moving with
exactly the same velocity backwards
there's some frame of
reference not moving as fast as a train
not standing as still as close to you
somebody riding a bicycle who is sort of
midway between the two reference frames
and that they see me going with velocity
something and you going backward with
the same velocity that person sees a
entirely symmetric
situation entirely symmetric situation
and what you will see we'll see the two
meter sticks approaching each other with
exactly the same velocity two meter
sticks in the perpendicular Direction
approaching each other with exactly the
same velocity and since the situation is
entirely symmetric between the left and
the right there's no expectation that
one of the meter sticks will pass the
other one looking shorter than it
they'll pass each other looking exactly
the same length and so for that reason
uh there's no funny business about X and
Y sorry Y and Z but x and t get mixed up
with each
other okay let me show you another way
to write the lorence transformation
which might uh be Illuminating it gives
you a little bit of a geometric picture
about how these equations
work let's come over to this Blackboard
over
here uh first of all let's get rid of
the speeds of light in them because
they're a nuisance let's just set it
equal to
one just for Simplicity and now let's
add these two equations on both
sides what we'll get on the left hand
side is X Prime + T Prime that's the
left hand side what will we get on the
right hand side we're going to get first
of all something with the same
denominator so what we get is going to
have a denominator Square < TK of 1us V
^2 and then in the numerator it looks
like we'll get x +
T but then we're going to get another
term which is going to be minus V * x +
T so that will be x + T * 1 -
v x + T and then minus V * x + T all
right 1 over 1 - V sorry 1 - V /un 1 -
v^ 2 what's that let's work it out over
here 1 -
V
upstairs and then Square < TK of 1us V
Square downstairs that's the same as the
square < TK of 1 - V * 1 -
V that's just one minus v i just rewrote
one minus V divided by the square T of 1
- V * 1 +
V 1 - v s is 1 - V * 1 + V the 1 minus V
is cancel and and all of this is just
equal to the square Ro T of 1 - V over 1
+
V okay so first of all let me rewrite
this equation it says that X Prime + T
Prime is equal to x +
T times something which depends on the
velocity and it depends on the velocity
as 1 minus V over 1 + V
now let's look at X Prime minus t
Prime right now let's look at X Prime
minus t Prime instead of X Plus t x
prime plus T Prime and let's see what we
get X Prime minus t
Prime right when we subtract them we're
going to get an x minus t from here and
we're going to get a plus v because
we're
subtracting
um X you know I want to do I just want
to I want to make a small change in this
I want to write this as T Prime + x
Prime same thing I haven't changed
anything t plus X it's just because it
agrees with my
notes and now I want to write this one
as T Prime minus X
Prime T Prime minus X Prime that's to
subtract this from this what do we get
then we
get T minus X
Time 1 +
V / the square < TK of 1 - V ^ 2 we'll
get a 1 + V because of the opposite sign
that appears here let's see we'll get T
minus X and then we'll get minus V * x -
t that all adds up to a 1 + V / < TK of
1 - v^2 but if you go through the same
exercise here 1 + V
1 + V 1 + V what you get is square < TK
of 1 + V over 1 minus
V it looks almost the same as the
equation for x Prime + T Prime but with
a slight difference that the square root
that appears here is square < TK of 1 +
V over 1 minus V now let's stop now and
look at what we have instead of working
with x and t I've worked with new
coordinates new coordinates X+ T and xus
T you know what you can think of those
as
if this is T and this is
X and 45° remember represents the motion
of light rays then X Prime + T prime or
X Plus T is a coordinate along that axis
and xus T is a coordinate along this
axis this is the x + T coordinate and
this is the x or the T minus x
coordinate what this is telling
us is that x + T when it's Loren
transformed just gets multiplied by
something that depends on the velocity
and at the same time T minus X also just
gets multip M lied by something but that
something is the
inverse the something here is one over
the something here so one picture of
what these mathematical Transformations
are like is that t + x depending on
whether V is positive or negative t + x
gets
stretched that's what this says it's
either get stretched or squeezed
depending on the let's see if V is
positive then 1 minus V is less than one
this would be less than one that would
say that this transformation squeezes t
+ x t Prime + x Prime is t + x * a
number less than one so it squeezes one
axis and stretches the other axis axis
by the inverse
amount so for example a loren
transformation with the appropriate
velocity would squeeze this axis by a
factor of two and double this axis by a
factor of two that's the nature of
lorence Transformations they're really
quite simple they're stretching along
one axis one 45° axis and squeezing
along the other 45° axis but notice the
important thing is they don't change the
45° axes the 45 degre axes stay 45° why
is that
important because that tells you that
light rays continue to move move with a
speed of light in any reference frame so
you see Len Transformations are really
quite simple they are stretching along
one axis a squeezing along the other
axis but they preserve the 45° axes they
don't preserve other lines in here other
lines will get stretched this way and
squeeze the other direction but the ones
which are along the 45 degree axis do
are maintained so that's the nature of
luren Transformations sort of a
squashing
of One lightlike Direction and expansion
of the other lightlike
direction uh along the direction of
motion of the Rel the relative motion of
the two reference
frames all right any questions about the
structure of Lorent Transformations
before we go on
yeah
yeah okay
there one has to make some assumptions
but
um the assumption is that if two objects
cross at an instant of SpaceTime if two
events are at the same instant of
SpaceTime and now that would mean for
example when these two meter sticks
cross each other a flash of light could
go off from each from the end of each
one at the moment that they hit each
other we call that an event if an event
occurs at a particular SpaceTime Point
uh or if two events occur at the same
SpaceTime point in one reference frame
then they occur at the same SpaceTime
point at another reference frame so
that's that's an added ingredient that's
sort of if if you really Trace every
possible assumption I'm sure there's an
infinite number of assumptions hidden
things like that but they're also easy
to believe that uh that if two events in
SpaceTime no
yes if two events in SpaceTime occur at
the same SpaceTime location according to
one Observer then they occur at the same
space time according to another Observer
the notion of an event an event a point
of space time at which a thing could
occur that's an invariant concept and so
you could bring it back to the question
of the
events of the crossing of these two
meter sticks yeah doesn't the Bic also
have to be in the middle of the the met
stick uh in the middle of the meter
stick can see well the bicycle list of
course stands for a whole moving frame
of reference
me well or he can see the flashes of
light come out from the when the two
meter sticks crash into each other he
can see the flashes of light come out
and then deduce that the flashes of
light came out from the same two point
from the same points so I don't think he
really has to be right there but he has
to be able to deduce what was going on
right there by looking at the light rate
so so what does he see you see two meter
sticks come past each other and then
sees a pair of flashes of light
emanating from exactly the same points
two flashes four flashes altogether one
from the right end of this meter stick
one from the left end of this meter
stick one from the right end of this
meter stick one from the left end and
sees that these two rays of light
emanate from the same point in SpaceTime
and the other two back on my shoulders
here which I can't squeeze together I'm
not as flexible as I used to
be okay so um that's Lorent
Transformations what I forgot to do
which we'll do next time was to show you
how to compound
velocities uh we'll do that next time um
but for the next
thing I want to tell you about proper
time now I don't remember I don't think
we talked about proper time last time
many of you know what proper time is
some of you don't but let's spell it
out as I
said Newton believed that time was the
same for
everybody moving stationary accelerated
whatever you do time will agree if you
synchronize two clocks whatever you do
with them thereafter they will stay
synchronized if you have a whole
collection of synchronized clocks they
will stay
synchronized um that as we will see is
not true for moving clocks in the
special theory of relativity and there's
a notion of time which is proper time
now here's what proper time
means
it you're going to take a walk you're
going to walk around you're going to
walk around with a high velocity upward
KNE the speed of light but you carry
your wristwatch with you okay everybody
sitting still has their own time piece
and the sitting still people all
synchronize their time pieces so that
they all agree they synchronize their
time pieces with light rays and
according to the way that Einstein
described synchronizing light rays so
you people all have perfectly
synchronized light Ray sorry perfectly
synchronized
clocks and I have my clock and I start
walking around at first when I start
I've synchronized my clock with yours we
all agree and then I walk around and I
take a walk around the table a few times
at close to the speed of
light and at the end I look at my time
piece and you and I compare it with the
time piece of the person standing next
to me over here in general there's no
reason for them to agree and they won't
agree the proper time of my moving clock
is the time read by the moving clock
okay the coordinate time this is
definitions the coordinate time is the
time measured by your stationary clocks
so proper time is something which sort
of follows the Observer around and ticks
off intervals of proper
time
uh as a clock following as a wristwatch
would uh would tick off instance of time
all right let me uh give you the formula
for proper
time and then show you the proper time
is an invariant concept the proper time
between two events we're talking about
now two events we could think of them as
two events along a trajectory if we
wanted the trajectory could be the
trajectory of a moving clock but for the
moment let's just think of them as two
events and one of them for Simplicity
let's take at the
origin so the origin of
coordinates so this point over here is
xal 0 t = 0 x Prime equal 0 t Prime
equal 0 notice incidentally where's our
Len transformation we seem to have lost
them let me write them back over here uh
x = X - v x Prime = x -
VT over < TK of 1 - V ^ 2 T Prime is
equal to t - VX over < TK 1 - v^ 2
notice that when x and t are both equal
to zero X Prime and T Prime are also
equal to zero so we set it up in such a
way that the origin of SpaceTime
coordinates is the same for both
observers okay so here's our moving
Observer or let this not even be a
moving Observer it's just a moving
particle or a moving person it doesn't
have to correspond to a to a uh a
reference frame it's just some object
moving and it could be moving with an
accelerated velocity but let's just take
a small piece of its trajectory along
which we can approximate it by a
straight
line okay
now if we replaced SpaceTime by ordinary
space if we replaced it by ordinary
space forget this and just think about
ordinary space not x and t but X and
Y we could also have different
coordinates describing
the
same X Prime and Y Prime namely
coordinates which were just rotated
relative to the original
coordinates what kinds of things are the
same for both I'll call them observers
but I simply mean rotated coordinate
frames well one very invariant quantity
is the distance from the
origin the distance from the origin of
any point
necessarily is the same in both
coordinate frames right that's clear
your distance from me doesn't depend on
which way I'm oriented right I have my X
and my y doesn't matter which way I'm
oriented you're still sitting 3 m or 3
or 4 meters from me no matter which way
I turn so that
implies that the distance from the
origin the square let's take the square
of the distance from the origin call it
2 that's equal to x^2 + y^2 it must also
be equal to X Prime 2 + y Prime
squ in other words the quantity x^2 +
y^2 is the
same in any coordinate system ordinary
coordinate system involving the rotation
of
coordinates something like that is true
for Loren
Transformations something slightly
different a little slightly different
mathematical expression this is X this
is
T and this is some point here with
coordinates XT
or X Prime T Prime depending on which
frame of reference I'm looking at that
event the statement which we can work
out from this equation here in fact
let's do it let's do
it let's take
the point XT which could also be labeled
by the prime coordinates and work out
the quantity X Prime
squar not t Prime 2 + x Prime SAR but T
Prime squar minus X prime
squar a little bit of a glitch on what
we would do if we were just rotating
coordinates P Prime 2 - x Prime s let's
write it on the right here first of all
in denominator we'll get 1 - V ^2
because we've squared everything all
right now let's look at X Prime squ that
has
X2 it has plus v ^2
t^2 and then it has Min
-2 x v
t that's oh that's X Prime squar huh
that's that comes in with a minus sign
here but then let's add in t Prime squ T
Prime squ has t^2 + v^2
x^2 minus 2x
VT also divided by 1 -
v^2 all right so this is T Prime squar
this is X Prime squar and we subtract
them the first thing that we
notice is that these things these cross
terms
cancel when we subtract these two the
cross terms
cancel now the X squares don't cancel
because here we have v^2 x^2 -
x^2 right so that's
minus 1 -
v^2
x^2 and then what about the t^2 term is
t^2 here minus or minus v^ 2 t^2 so
that's
t^2 * 1 - v^ s all over 1us V
^2 to make a long story
short let's write it out T Prime 2 - x
Prime 2 is equal to T ^2 -
x^2 just work it out if you didn't
follow the little bit of algebra here
just work it out square this Square this
subtract them in either way and you'll
find out that t Prime 2 - x Prime 2 is
the same as t^2 x - x^2 very very much
like when you rotate
coordinates the square of the distance
stays the same the square of the
distance from the origin stays the same
now a physicist would say that means
that the quantity T ^2 - x^2 is
invariant it's the same no matter
whether you look at it from the point of
view of the primed frame or the unprimed
frame and it has a name because it's
invariant it's important anything which
is invariant and which is the same for
all observers must have a special
importance it's uh it's something which
everybody will agree upon and so we
ought to give it a name the name for it
is proper time the proper time between
this point and this point proper time
the proper
time between the origin and the point
XT is by definition proper
time is equal to the square root of T ^2
-
x^2 why the square root well it's the
it's very similar to the it's a
definition of course it's a definition
we could have worked with a definition
where the proper time was just uh t^2 -
x^2 but it's a definition to take the
square root but it's very much like
looking at the distance between two
points and using Pythagoras's Theorem
the uh Pythagorean theorem says that the
distance between the points is the
square root of X2 + y^2 all right so in
parallel with that we call this the
proper time between the origin and the
point
XT and that as I said is definition but
it's a highly useful definition and
we'll see why it's useful as we go along
the main thing about it is that
everybody agrees about it okay first of
all let's look at some possible
values that the proper time can have for
various points
XT if T is bigger than
x what does it mean for t to be bigger
than
x in magnitude if t^2 is bigger than X2
if t^2 is bigger than x
squ that means we're talking about
points which are in a wedge here where
time where the time component is larger
than the X component t^2 is larger than
X2 all in here
but let's in particular stay in the
upper half uh space here t^2 is bigger
than X2 if you're within this
wedge okay the wedge is the light
cone oh I should add in yes I should add
something in if we are working in three
dimensions not not sorry three spatial
Dimensions not one spatial Dimension
then we should also add in minus y^ 2
minus z^2 here
- y Prime 2us Z Prime
s that makes sure that our definitions
don't depend on Direction and space as
long as we know that we're only talking
about lench Transformations along a
given axis we don't really have to worry
about Y and Z but if we wanted to do
Loren Transformations along some other
axis and we wanted to add in Y and Z we
would note that this whole quantity T
Prime s - x Prim s - y sare - Z Prime s
is invariant why is that incidentally
well remember that Z Prime and Y Prime
don't
transform when we go from one frame of
reference along the x-axis to another
and so that doesn't make any difference
if we put in y Prime and Z Prime here
but it's a convenience to add it in and
then we have an expression here which
doesn't depend on Direction in space but
if you only want to think more simply
about Direction
along a single axis then you don't have
to worry about Y and Z okay so here we
are this this point here t^2 is greater
than x^2 and that means that t^2 - x^2
is positive and the square root of a
positive number is a is a is another uh
another real
number so in this Tim likee region this
is called the timik region because the
coordinates are more in the direction of
time than they are in space in the Tim
like region the proper time is just a
positive number square root of a
positive number and we take the positive
square root so T so that's perfectly
normal positive proper time up in here
what about along the L cone along the L
cone that's exactly where X is either
equal to T or X is equal to minus t
along here x is equal to T along here x
is equal to minus t whoops X is equal to
minus
t so in either case T ^2 is equal to
x^2 so along the light cone along the
place where light rays can travel the
proper distance between or the proper
time between the origin and that point
is zero now this is a big difference
between ordinary distance and proper
time ordinary distance if the distance
between two points is zero those points
are the same point there's no way that
the distance between two points can be
zero and then not be sitting on top of
each
other in manowski space in the space
describing the special theory of
relativity the space time two points can
have zero proper distance between them
or zero proper time between them
and still not be the same point here and
here right what is true is that if two
points are separated by zero proper time
then a light Ray can go from one to the
other so the trajectories of light rays
correspond to
paths
which have essentially zero proper time
along
them real particles sorry not real
particles but Mass but particles moving
with less than the speed of
light have
trajectories which are in a Tim likee
Direction like that they're moving
slower than the speed of light and the
proper time along those is positive now
let me prove a simple
thing proper
time
measures ordinary time as seen by a a
clock moving with the object for example
supposing we have a clock which is at
rest a clock which is at rest in our
frame just has a Vertical World line
it's perfectly at
rest and for such
a point let's take a point along here
what's the proper time from the origin
it's the Square t of T ^2 -
x^2 but X is0 for this point so it's
just the square root of t^2 which is
just
T so the proper time along a trajectory
which is standing still is just the
ordinary
time what does that tell you that tells
you that the proper
time is nothing but the time read by a
wristwatch standing
still what about what about the proper
time along a trajectory which has a
finite velocity for example supposing it
has a finite velocity like
that and we look at the proper time for
particular point over
here well the principle of Relativity
the equivalence between different
reference frames tells us the following
thing we could always think of
this particle object Observer as being
at rest we could always do a Loren
transformation so this guy is the guy at
rest and then use the same logic that we
use the second ago in the reference
frame where this is at
rest this point here would have X Prime
equals 0 but T Prime not equal to
zero why is it X Prime equal to zero
because in the moving reference frame
moving with this guy over here this
whole trajectory corresponds to his
origin of coordinates so X Prime would
be zero for somebody moving along this
trajectory here but T Prime would not be
zero over here and we could work out
exactly the same argument the proper
time to this point over here would be T
Prime SAR minus X Prime
squar but X Prime squ is zero and so the
proper time along here in the same way
as along here as along the vertical
trajectory measures the time as read by
a moving watch a moving clock moving
clocks tick off proper
time
uh that's the message that the meaning
of proper time is nothing but the
meaning of the the the time as read by a
watch which is moving with the moving uh
object all right so that's the notion of
proper time
it's kind of funny in these regions over
here in these regions over here X is
bigger than T and so t^2 - x^2 is
negative and the proper time is
imaginary points up in here are called
Tim like relative to the origin points
along the light cone here are called
liti and points out here are called
space likee spacelike points have an
imaginary proper distance an imaginary
proper time relative to the origin but
points in the within the light cone have
a real proper time okay any questions
about the notion of proper time it's
very similar to distance along a
trajectory except with a funny property
that there's a minus sign that you throw
in here A minus sign that you throw in
instead of a plus
sign t^2 -
x^2 but it has many similar properties
and in particular it's the same in every
reference frame the proper time between
two two distinct points is
invariant now we can use that fact we
can use that fact and fact similar to it
well
that the time interval between two
points the time interval as read by a
clock that moves between those two
points well just you were using same you
was using the same word for both
interval and reading
the
uh
okay I meant time interval but uh
yeah yeah so to put it another way if
there are two points in
SpaceTime and a clock a physical real
clock can move from one to the other
along a straight trajectory that means a
trajectory with constant uh
velocity then the difference of time
readings at the two ends of the
trajectory over here will be the proper
time in other words the dist the
difference between the time read at this
point and at that point will be the
proper time along that trajectory you
can calculate then if I give you two
points in
SpaceTime we can calculate very easily
how long it takes to move between these
two points as read by the moving clock
not as read by stationary clocks that's
different as read by stationary clocks
the time difference is just whatever the
time was at this point and whatever the
time was at this point where the times
were just
um
te but the moving clock the moving clock
reads its own
time that's the message of special
relativity that the rate at which clocks
move depends on how they move now we can
work out in some detail the relationship
between moving clocks and stationary
clocks let's do that and the tool is to
use proper
time
so let's take a
clock which starts at the
origin and moves along a trajectory
which takes it to a
point let's call let's takes it to a
point on the origin of the moving
coordinates I'm sorry that line does not
look very straight does it I intended it
to be a straight
line here we have our moving coordinate
frame and a clock moves from the origin
to a point over here now what is that
point over here that point over here is
X Prime equal
0 it's the origin of spatial coordinates
for the moving
Observer and it's some point T
prime it also has
coordinates x
t in other words in the stationary
reference frame it has coordinates XT in
the moving frame it has coordinates X
Prime equal 0 and some T
Prime I would like to know if I know X
and I know T what is T
Prime
incidentally X of course is equal to
VT so really all I need to know is T and
the velocity of the moving Observer is's
the moving
Observer his trajectory is xal
VT here's T and here's xal VT okay what
is the time r
by the clock moving from here to here
what is T Prime well now that's easy to
find out T Prime 2 - x Prime 2 must
equal T ^2 -
x what a t sorry this should be prime T
Prime s - x Prime s should equal T ^2 -
x^2 for this point why because the
expression for proper time is in
variant okay same expression in either
reference frame for the proper time
between this point and the origin what
do I know about this point I know that
it's X Prime is equal to zero so let's
cancel that out no let's not cancel that
out let's just rewrite it t Prime
squar
equals
t^2 but now at this point x is equal to
VT so that's minus v²
T
^2 well that's interesting we now have a
simple formula for T
Prime first of all let's write that as 1
minus V * T
^2 1 - V ^
2 *
t^2 well we just take the square root T
Prime the time read by the moving
clock is equal to the time time read by
the stationary
clock the time read by the stationary
clock is just this time here times 1 - <
TK 1 - V
^2 that's the famous formula of time
dilation that when you see a moving
clock that moving clock will appear to
move a little bit slow why slow because
1 minus V ^2 is less than one but
everybody will agree about the value of
the proper time between these two points
although they will disagree about the
actual coordinate times in
particular the the coordinate time T
Prime seen the moving reference frame
will be the coordinate time is in the in
the um in the stationary reference frame
time < TK of 1 - V ^2 so what that says
is that the moving Observer well the
stationary the stationary observers will
see the moving clock run a little bit
slow we really should at this point put
in the speeds of light c^
s v^2 over c^2 is typically a very very
small
number so this is almost T Prime equals
T but with a slight discrepancy this is
the time dilation of a moving
clock now how come how can it possibly
be that we have relativity which says
there's a complete parallel between or a
complete symmetry between the moving
Observer and the stationary Observer how
do we then account for the fact that the
stationary Observer sees the moving
Observer having having his time slowed
down what uh what does that mean if we
look at it the other way what does the
moving Observer see about the stationary
Observer does he see the stationary
observers time sped up no also sees the
time slowed down so if I move past you
with my clock my clock seems to slow
down as far as you're concerned on the
other hand if I watch one of you and I
have all of my fellows lined up with me
forming a reference frame they will also
see your clock go slow how can that
possibly be that sounds
contradictory well they're talking about
two different
things the moving Observer remember that
the moving
Observer his
time or his lines along which time are
constant are not these horizontal lines
here they're lines which look like
this this is T Prime equals a constant
this is T Prime equals a constant and so
forth so the lines on which T Prime are
constant are different than the lines on
which T are constant this is this
relativity of synchronicity the
relativity of being
synchronous different observers called
different things synchronous now let's
take the moving Observer
here and the moving observer
looks at the stationary clocks at an
instant of his time and asks what does
the stationary clock read well an
instant of his time looks like
this so he's really asking not what the
stationary clock reads at this point but
what if the stationary clock reads at
that
point so there are two different
questions when you
ask what one Observer sees of the other
one's
clock uh there is a complete symmetry
let's see how to say this I think I've
already said it but um um let's try to
say it more clearly we're comparing
different things the surfaces along
which T is constant and along which T
Prime is constant are different surfaces
and so when you ask whether whether
clocks are synchronous or not
synchronous and so forth you have to
account for this difference in what you
mean by synchronous that's
all so the that's the time dilation the
fact that moving clocks appear to
stationary observers to go slow
and stationary clocks appear to moving
observers also to go
slow we could have been certain from the
beginning that whatever one observa sees
of the others clock that they will be
reciprocal because of the reciprocal
nature of Lorent
Transformations okay that's the slowing
down of
clocks let's talk about about the twin
paradox somebody asked me about the twin
paradox we're now in a good position
to uh to do the twin paradox and see
what it
says let's work it
out the twin
paradox two twins are born at the origin
of coordinates one stays home it means
stays at rest doesn't move doesn't
accelerate doesn't move at all and just
moves along a trajectory like that a
world line like that uh the other one is
shot out at a high velocity not quite
the velocity of light at a high
velocity for a certain period and then
at the end of that period turns around
and comes
back and meets the
twin at that point there
they compare their clocks well all kinds
of clocks they could compare their
clocks their watches their heartbeats
their aging rate their metabolic uh time
differences between here and here uh how
long their beards are or whatever
whatever corresponds to a good clock
they compare their clocks at this point
and ask what the relationship between a
Time Red by a clock moving here and a
Time Red by a clock moving here well
we're all set up to calculate it now
because all we have to do is to
calculate the proper time between this
point and this point along the vertical
trajectory and the proper time along
this uh trajectory which consists of two
different pieces we just add up the
proper time from here to here and the
proper time from here to here and that
will tell us what the clocks measure
clocks measure proper time all right
first of all this triangle assuming that
the Observer that the the second Twin
comes back with the same velocity that
he was shot out with with some velocity
V then this triangle is a nice isoceles
triangle and we can divide this vertical
line in half call this side T this half
side T it takes therefore time 2
T in the ref from the uh stationary
person here it takes time 2T to go from
this world point to this world point and
therefore the person who stays home says
it took amount of time twice capital T
for my twin to return all right so
that's twice capital
T that's what the Observer who stays
home says the time interval between
birth and meeting the twin is now what
about the twin who goes out and comes
back let's uh calculate what the total
proper time is along this trajectory
here he goes out with velocity
V how far out does he get he gets out a
distance V *
t v * T is the distance along the x-axis
that the moving twin gets out so this
point then has
coordinates X = VT and time T let's
calculate the proper time from here to
here the proper time the square of the
proper time is is T ^2 - x^2 so the
proper time along the first leg of the
journey here is
t^2 minus v^2 t
^2 which is equal to 1 - V ^
2 time
t^2 that's the square of the proper time
we have to take the square root of it to
find out how much the clock changed from
here to here and so the time change the
proper time along this trajectory here
is square TK of 1 - v^ 2 * T what about
on the second leg of the journey the
second leg of the journey is exactly
parallel to this first uh to the first
leg of the journey except going backward
the proper time between here and here is
exactly the same as the proper time
between here and here there's the same x
coordinate and the same
T so the answer for the Observer going
along this bent trajectory here is twice
this twice T * < TK of 1 - V ^2 as
opposed to just twice
T which one is smaller the smaller one
the smaller proper time is
associated with the twin who got shot
out and came back why because 1 - v^2 is
smaller than one so the amount of time
read off by the moving clocks here is
smaller by Factor square root of 1 minus
v^2 than the time measured along the uh
trajectory of the twin who stayed
home all kinds of
times as I said the length of the beard
the number of heartbeats all sorts of
things the time read along this moving
trajectory will be less and the
consequence is that the moving um the
moving twin comes back looking younger
feeling younger looking younger being
younger than the than the twin stayed
home now is this a
paradox it's not a paradox because
there's nothing inconsistent about it
doesn't look inconsistent there's
nothing particularly inconsistent
sometimes people ask how do you tell
which twin moved and which twin didn't
move well that's not hard this twin
reversed his trajectory and accelerated
at this point over here
and so if they were in a rocket ship
they would feel the rocket ship
accelerate and there is no symmetry
between the two twins one twin just
stays at home experiences no
acceleration experiences no tendency to
be thrust back and forth by the
acceleration of whatever uh he's sitting
in the other twin suddenly experiences a
sharp acceleration at this point and so
there's no symmetry between
them uh there's no more of a
contradiction
then asking about the sides of a
triangle the distance
along the side of a triangle is not the
same as the distance along the uh broken
path composed of the other two sides
there's no no more nothing more
paradoxical than
that the proper distance along the sides
of these two triang
broken trajectory here is just different
than the proper distance along here now
Newton would not have understood that or
at least probably Newton would have
understood it if it was explained to him
he was certainly smart enough but uh
with his own view of time and his own
view of space this would have been a
shock to discover that a twin that goes
out and comes back comes back
younger uh than the twin who stayed home
yeah
question typical question so at that
point the physics is
well the the twin feels something quite
different no you don't argue around it
there's acceleration there but then you
don't know any longer if this analysis
about clocks is correct okay um the
Assumption first of all you can smooth
this out there's nothing there was
nothing uh uh there was nothing very
special about making this a sharp turn
all right all right to say that it's
smoothed out just says that there's a a
finite acceleration rather than an
instantaneous infinite acceleration
that's good as I said the assumption is
that the clocks that we have the way
that they tick is insensitive to
acceleration all right now this isn't
true of real clocks real clocks if you
accelerate them too hard they'll break
right if you accelerate your clock real
hard you'll break it now it also depends
on the size of a clock the bigger the
clock is if you give it a hard
acceleration the easier it is to break
it if you take a tiny tiny tiny little
clock and you accelerate it it's harder
to break taking an atom and accelerating
it at 10 m/s per second the the atomic
uh clock that's composed of the electron
going around the nucleus is not going to
be affected by that 10 meters per second
per second
on the other hand a great big clock uh
100 miles wide and so forth that's that
you try to accelerate
it uh it's going to be very very
delicate to accelerate it without
changing the way that it ticks okay so
the assumption is that the clocks tick
off proper time right that's an
assumption that
good faithful small clocks which are
very well built and built to withstand
acceleration that they simply tick off
proper time if they take off proper time
all we have to do is measure the proper
time along there now as I said we can do
this experiment in a way that minimizes
the amount of acceleration here we don't
need a lot of
acceleration we can have um we can have
during this period here the acceleration
be very modest it could be a small
fraction of the 10 m/s per second that
we feel in this room here we don't
normally think that that 10 m per second
per second has any any very big
significance and any big um effect on
our wrist watches if we swing our arm
around a little bit we can swing it
around at more than 10 m/ second per
second if the clock is built to
withstand shock and so forth then the
acceleration won't have much effect on
it and so the assumption is that the
acceleration doesn't have much effect on
the clock and the meaning of that is
that the clock always ticks off proper
time uh so it ticks off the number of
units of proper time along the
trajectory now that is an assumption
there is assumption it's the Assumption
of an ideal clock it is what you mean by
an ideal
clock does that help
Isis
yeah without
acceler yes sign yes yes
yes
right seems like the analysis way breaks
down
the the analysis the analysis the logic
of the analysis the logic of the
analysis has to be supplemented with
some additional physical
facts uh that I don't think you can
derive just from what we said but we
derive them from the experience of
knowing that if we have a small clock
wellmade built to resist the shock and
so forth that uh as a matter of
experience we know that that clock's
rate of ticking will not be sensitive to
modest accelerations will not be
particularly sensitive
yeah so if you threw a clock up let it
come back down yeah you would get the
same sort of answer if you slung it
around the star like yeah yeah but would
you kid no no no no no you see it's not
going to help to say general relativity
because then what you're going to be
asking is what is the effect of GRA of
the gravitational field on the on the
way the clock uh
behaves and I can't answer that unless I
know more about the clock I have to know
the details of how the Clock Works and
so forth again if the clock is a big
sloppy clock made out of very big
components and the components which
aren't very rigid and so forth then it's
going to be very sensitive to
acceleration on the one hand but it's
also going to be if I put it on the
table here it's also going to be
squashed down by the uh by the
gravitational field and so it will also
fail to uh to be a good faithful clock
if I take a small hard
clock uh you know by hard I mean
hardened against
acceleration then number one it will
report faithful timekeeping if I put it
on the table in the gravitational field
number two it will report faithful
timekeeping if I swing and around my
head on a rope but I can't I can't prove
that from the things that we've done
from the mathematics we've done I can
say that's a matter of experience and a
matter of physics and a matter of how
clocks are made
and what they're made out of and so
forth yeah but what you've been talking
about here is what I would call say the
mechanics of the clock yeah you have to
right but there's the other thing which
is I don't know the proper word the
fabric of space under acceleration right
which is a different okay right right so
if to the extent that we talk about the
fabric of space what we would be talking
about here would be proper time
measurements along this uh along this
trajectory here the fabric of space or
whatever the right word for it is the
geometry of SpaceTime the geometry of
SpaceTime is a geometry of proper times
and proper distances what you're saying
then is you
can I can reduce the thing to small
intervals so oh yes interal absolutely
absolutely I that was implicit that was
implicit I should have made that
explicit yes absolutely indeed yes we
yes I should have I should have been
explicit about that right we divide the
trajectory into small little segments
Each of which has approximately a very
uh constant velocity along that little
segment we calculate the proper time
along that segment we add it to the
proper time along the next segment we
add it to the proper time along the next
segment but it's very very similar
mathematics to the way that we would
calculate the length along a curve we
calculate the length along a curve by
dividing it up into a a lot of little
intervals and for each interval
calculating the length by X2 + y^2 or
Delta X2 plus Delta y^2 square root add
them all up and that gives us the length
along the curve in very much the same
way we take this curved trajectory and
we divide it into small little intervals
each interval can be thought of as
almost a straight line and therefore
each
interval uh uh can be analyzed by
thinking of it as having a constant
velocity and along those that trajectory
we add up all the constant times is that
what the question was is that why we
were
um no I I know exactly what you're
asking the way to analiz that is to
imagine actually sending light rays back
and forth uh let's tick off some time
intervals here well let's let's imagine
ticking off 1 second intervals along
both trajector
1 second intervals of proper time along
both
trajectories so here would 1 second
intervals might look something
approximately like this for the
stationary
person this isn't very many seconds so
it's not going to grow a very long
beard right and one second intervals
would be longer long here because the
moving clocks appear to go slow to the
stationary
Observer they might go a little bit
faster in this
right so it look like that okay now we
could start sending light signals back
and forth every
instant the stationary Observer could
send a light signal to the moving
Observer now look what would happen the
first set of light signals that was sent
early would come to the moving Observer
stretched
out this is Doppler shift this is
Doppler shift shift in fact but we don't
even have to think about it as Doppler
shift if this guy is moving
fast he sees the light coming the series
of light pulses coming from the
stationary Observer coming um delayed
very delayed at first and then all
lumped up not delayed but squeezed
together in the second part of the
trajectory here so he sees all the light
signals the 1 2 3 four five six or six
or five light signals but sees the first
set of them come very slowly and the
last set of them come very quickly now
what about the stationary Observer
looking at the moving Observer the
moving Observer may also send out light
signals and also there would be kind of
Doppler shifts but the number of light
signals that the stationary Observer
sees would equal the number of light
signals that the moving Observer sent
out and the number of light signals that
the moving Observer sees would equal the
number of light signals that the
stationary Observer sees so in both
cases they would see something taking
place uh somewhat irregularly in time at
first they would see things stretched
out and slowed down okay and then they
would see things speeded up in both
cases but at slightly different rates
and rates which would
um which
would which you can calculate but they
won't see any missing frames by missing
frames you would mean missing light
signals they would see all each one
would see all the light signals that the
other one sent out but coming at rates
which would depend on their state
relative state of
motion does that answer your
question it's of as
there when you're talking about D or
something else kind of bothers me if if
the person the astronaut coming back
sees it shift sees the light shifted
let's say the the first person is first
T he transmits light that's of a low
frequency this person transmits light of
low frequency yeah the person coming
back when he collects the light would he
be colleting more energy than was I mean
I'm sure the answer is no but it sounds
like it would be actually collecting
more energy okay before we can answer
that we have to know more about energy
so let's wait on that kind of question
until we know something in energy at the
moment all we're talking about is x's
and T's but it's a reasonable question
what are what uh uh how does the
energetics appear to both observers and
answer is is that energy really only
makes sense in the usual sense to an
observer who is not accelerated to talk
about the energy of the moving of the
accelerated Observer is very tricky and
uh
y you got to talk
loud
you that have a concept ofal Dimensions
that are Cur up in that case two
TS
only without any of them doing what
without
accelerating oh oh oh oh oh yes but
there would nevertheless be an asymmetry
between the one that went around the uh
uh the direction and the one Stood
Still uh
well the moving Observer would discover
a surprise he would discover that he
kept repetitively uh passing through the
same
places um you know if we were moving on
a
circle we and uh we would discover that
repetitively we keep passing the same
place we have I have to think about that
that's a good question but the answer is
definitely that they're asymmetric that
they're asymmetric the person moving
around the closed loop and the one
standing
still
uh
no no no no that is
not quite right
um good let's come back to it give me I
need to think about the good answer to
that it's a nice question I want give me
some time to think about it uh uh I
don't want to give you I don't want to
give you an unthought out answer so let
me come back to it does everybody
understand what the question was the
question is an interesting one uh yeah
um supposing you lived in a
world
of two dimensions of space two
dimensions of space uh this was only a
world of one dimension of
space and your world was a cylinder
a cylinder of
space okay now this is space this is not
SpaceTime you can imagine such a world
special
relativity doesn't actually quite make
sense for it there's a problem with
special relativity here uh but let's
suppose perfect special relativity made
sense then an observer could stay home
over here and another one
could move around in a trajectory that
uh well sorry this isn't time vertical
isn't time vertical is space one
Observer could just stand there stand
still and the other could go around at a
large velocity and then come back that
Observer who was moving around with a
large velocity it would be unnecessary
for him to experience any
acceleration and going around here just
moving with the same velocity and would
leave and come back without ever having
experienced any acceleration however it
is not true that they wouldn't
experience the fact that they were on
the uh on the um on the closed Contour
they would yeah you would experience
radial
acceleration sorry you would experience
radial acceleration moving around in
this closed curve here no no
no no no no no no no no no
this uh no no okay I see what you're
asking no you're not living in a world
which is a solid cylinder in which the
radius means anything you're just living
in a world which is just a pure surface
a pure surface there's no notion of
distance from the center here because
there's nothing in there let's come back
to it this is this is way way way beyond
what I wanted to discuss today kuta Kine
Theory this is not the this is
a a uh a somewhat more advanced uh
question what I did want to get
to before we quit is length contraction
we did time
dilation by doing proper time we do
length contraction in a very similar
way let's
uh look the first thing when you want to
understand the special relativity
problem is draw a picture always draw a
picture and see if you can't cast your
question in a diagrammatic
language uh which uh which you can then
answer by using Loren Transformations
and uh that sort of thing so let's
begin always start that way
always um for reference we put in a
light cone
that's the speed of light nothing moves
faster than the speed of
light okay now we have our moving
Observer have a stationary Observer we
have our moving
Observer here's the trajectory of the
moving Observer here is the surface of
constant time this is tal VX this is xal
VT one of these is a Surface along which
the moving observers clocks are all
synchronized this motion here is just
the origin of coordinates so the origin
of spatial coordinates of the moving
Observer and now let's imagine a meter
stick let's take a meter stick which is
at
rest in the rest frame so I need another
color let's see red might
do a meter stick which is at rest has
two ends let's take the Left End of the
meter stick left end of the meter stick
might start over here and it's at rest
so the left end of the meter stick is
over here the right end of the meter
stick is at x =
1 and it's over
here the meter stick sweeps
out A
Spacetime
strip at each instant of time the meter
stick is 1 M long But as time moves on
the a stick sweeps out a kind of ribbon
a ribbon through
SpaceTime all right now we want to know
what how long the moving Observer says
that the meeting the the meter stick is
how long is the meter stick according to
the moving Observer now what does the
moving Observer
mean the moving Observer means by the
length and this is of course a
definition to some extent the definition
of the length of the meter stick in the
moving frame of reference is the
following you take the two ends of the
meter stick at the same instant of time
but whose time the moving observer's
time the moving Observer takes the two
ends or looks at the two ends of the
meter stick at a synchronous time in his
own reference frame and asks in his own
reference frame how far apart is the
front end of the meter stick and the
rear end of the meter stick at a given
instant of
time well a given instant of time in the
in the uh moving reference frame means
this T equals
VX trajectory over here or this tal VX
surface over here so here's one end of
the meter stick at that instant of time
here's the other end of the meter stick
at the same instant of T Prime if you
like the in the in the stationary
reference frame these two points are
synchronous and the moving reference
frame these two points are synchronous
so if we want to know how long the meter
stick looks in the me in the moving
reference frame what we want to know is
not what the x of this point is but we
want to know what the X Prime of that
point
is we want to know what the XP Prime of
that point is which would be what the
moving Observer would call the length of
that meter stick now there's an easy way
to find out well one way to find out is
is just to compute where this point is
and then do a Lorent transformation to
find out what x Prime is but there's an
easier way and it's just to use proper
distance proper distance
means T ^2 - x^2 or the square of the
proper distance t s or x^2 minus t^2 it
doesn't matter one or the other and use
the fact that they're the same in the
two reference frames so let's take this
point over
here what is its proper distance
I won't call it proper time because it's
not Tim like but instead of looking at
t^2 - x^2 we could look at x sare minus
t^ s doesn't matter what is the
invariant distance four dimensional or
SpaceTime invariant distance between
this point and that point well on the
one hand if I work it out in the primed
frame of reference it's
just T Prime s - X Prime
squ that's the square of this proper
interval
here where this point has coordinates T
Prime and X Prime but what's the what's
the T Prime of this point the T Prime of
this point is zero this is the surface T
Prime equal
0 this whole surface corresponds to the
origin of time coordinates for the
moving Observer so along here T Prime is
equal to zero and the proper distance
from the origin is just or the square of
the proper distance is just minus X
Prime
squar on the other hand let's find the
unprimed coordinates of this
point this was supposed to be a meter
stick 1 meter long so this corresponds
to xal
1 xal 1 in the stationary reference
frame the stationary meter stick and the
stationary reference frame is exactly 1
M
long so this point corresponds the xal 1
this whole trajectory here what about
the what about the height of this point
that's T all right that's t equal VX all
along this trajectory so along here T is
equal
to just
V tal VX but x = 1 so along here this
point here is x = 1 T =
V all right so on the left hand side
here we have the proper distance
expressed in terms of primed
coordinates let's express it now in
terms of the unprimed coordinates that's
going to be t^2 which is V ^
minus x^2 which is
1 so what do we find out we discover
that the primed space coordinate of this
point over here is X Prime is equal to
the square < TK of 1 - V
^2 I've just changed the
sign and taken a square
root well that says that the moving that
the meter stick which is at rest in your
frame of reference and my frame of
reference appears to have length Square
< TK of 1 - v^2 another words the
coordinate distance between the two ends
of the meter stick in the moving
reference
frame is square < TK of 1us V
^2 X Prime at this point is zero X Prime
at this point is < TK of 1 - V ^2 so you
see what that says that says that the
stationary meter stick is seen in the
moving reference frame as having a
shorter
length again and application of the
invariance of the proper distance T
Prime 2 - x Prime 2 is equal to T ^2 -
x^2 that's what I've
used right let's just go through it
again for this point or first of all for
the first point on the left here
everything is equal to zero x t x Prime
T Prime they're all equal to zero and
that's trivial but this
point on the one hand T Prime is equal
to Z so we cross this
out on the other hand X is equal to 1
and T is equal to V so that gives us the
1 - V ^2 over here and it tells us that
X Prime is equal > 1 -
v^2
so the comparison of the length of the
meter sticks in the two reference frames
says that when a meter stick is at rest
a moving Observer sees it is being
shorter of course the converse is also
true and could be worked out in a
similar way the moving what did I say
yeah we said this the stationary meter
stick looks short to the moving Observer
the moving meter stick looks short to
the stationary Observer that's the
reciprocal character of um of Loren
Transformations okay any questions about
length contraction time
dilation uh Lorent transformations
or any of the geometry that we've done
yeah Does anything go spe light except
light no well yes
gravity do we know that no no do we know
it um
well we certainly know it within the
framework of the general theory of
relativity
yes yes within the framework of the
general theory of relativity uh yes do
we know it is an experimental
fact
um we really have never directly seen
gravitational
waves we'd like to see gravitational
waves but what we have seen is that the
effects of gravitational waves coming
from binary
pulsars and what's known about that
tends to suggest uh not terribly
strongly that light and gravity travel
with the same speed so no there's no
direct experimental evidence that
gravitational waves travel with the same
speed as uh as uh electromagnetic waves
on the other hand Einstein would have
had to been very wrong for not to for to
be untrue yeah from the perspective of
say an astronaut he can actually
accelerate faster than light you don't
wait accelerate faster than the speed of
light doesn't mean anything I mean Trel
as in let's say they wanted to get from
here to another star that's years yeah
they could um from their own
reference get there in less than four
years yes that's
true yes that's true and and the way to
see that is okay so here's a moving
Observer there's a moving Observer
here's star number one here's star
number two and that's four like years
away or whatever we want to find out how
long not in our stationary reference
frame it takes to get here but how long
does the moving Observer say that it
takes and for that we have to calculate
the proper time between here and here
now the point is that the proper time of
this point this point may be
T and
X the point is the proper time which is
t^2 the square of the proper time is T
^2 minus
x^2 that means it's always smaller than
just t^2 by itself so the proper time
between here and here is less than the
actual coordinate time so for that
reason yes you're absolutely right this
uh person over here would say that it
takes less time than uh than
uh than the four light years or whatever
it would be that the stationary Observer
would would uh from his perspective
wouldn't it wouldn't it also be right to
say that the
came to him well what what what the
moving Observer would
say is that he would what the moving
Observer would say he would put himself
first of all in his own frame of
reference and then he would look at the
two stars and he would see that the two
stars were a lot closer together than
what the stationary Observer
said so he would say it took a short
amount of time to go from one to the
other in other words the moving Observer
would see the Lorent contracted distance
between the stars and so would uh would
conclude that it took a small amount of
time to go from one star to the other
but to him that L contraction wouldn't
it look like the stars are traveling
faster than the feed of light no no the
Stars would not appear to be traveling
faster in the speed of light they would
appear to be traveling with exactly the
opposite
velocity the Stars see the astronaut
traveling with a certain velocity and
the astronaut sees the Stars traveling
with exactly the negative velocity uh
that
uh but when he starts out whens
Ates
me then yes but you have to ask when
he's moving how far apart does he see
the stars and moving with closer to the
speed of light then he sees the stars as
being not five light years or four light
years or whatever we said but four light
years times theare root of 1us V squ and
that in his reference frame would be the
description
so
later wa so sorry why does you start out
before
youel uh okay
so okay okay you're you're correct but
then we have to analyze a more
complicated problem the complicated
problem then starts with an observer
which which is at rest and they Again
The Observer starts to accelerate and
has to accelerate up to the up to the
this velocity and we have to take into
account this uh effects of acceleration
the simpler calculation to do is to
imagine an astronaut that was always
forever and ever moving with uniform
velocity remember the special theory of
relativity just like Newton's Theory
only makes sense in inertial reference
frames to find find out what happens in
a non-inertial reference frame we can
answer the question we can answer the
question but the question will not be
answered by application of exactly the
same formulas that we would use in an
inertial frame
start yeah yeah yeah yeah
absolutely yeah everything we've been
talking about is an inertial reference
frames to study non-inertial reference
frames we have to begin over again
and as you correctly point out uh
there's obviously going to be some
effects of acceleration which uh we have
to take into
account
okay yes so you would have the
twin for
examp wait wait sorry
again yes
oh
yeah yeah I mean if it wasn't born if it
wasn't born moving with a large velocity
yeah right right but you would still do
the same thing you would still calculate
the total proper time along his
trajectory yeah so the total proper time
would have contributions from different
velocities and we can work those out
they're they're simple to work out but
yes right no we assume one one twin is
born with a huge velocity and the other
one is
arrest oh the poor the poor woman I
mean very male audience today
I not to dwell on this issue of time but
uh it seems that all these problems that
we have are generated by the fact that
we put time in such a special place in
fact well we're going to see that time
is not in a special
place uh yeah we you you're right in the
back of our minds we tend to We tend to
isolate time as special but the lesson
of special relativity is the time is not
that
special
uh but we'll uh the real question is can
we recover all of the physics of slow
velocities that we normally know and
learn and love from our darwinian
circuits that we uh that we inherited
from uh from all the years that nothing
ever moved faster than 50 miles an hour
can we recover it by taking the formulas
from special relativity
and um specializing them to the case of
very slow velocities and yes of course
we
can I've also come to think about it in
way which is not only that it's special
but it's it's sort of elevated to the
level of a special Dimension fourth
dimension well is this necessary is it
necessary it's not only not necessary
Einstein never thought about that he
never said the time was the fourth
dimension it's not necessary to think of
time as the fourth dimension but once
you start mixing it up with uh space
where are our Loren Transformations
here there's an awful lot of the physics
which looks very symmetric between space
and time sort of pseudosymmetric t^2 -
x^2 - y^ 2 - z^ 2 they do get mixed up
with each other under uh under Lorent
transformations in a way that they
wouldn't under these Galilean
Transformations so here you see in
Galileo time really just is time whereas
in Einstein or lorence time really does
oh here it is time really does get mixed
up with space in a way that makes you
not want to uh think of it as
um fundamentally separate uh uh H
decoupled decoupled yeah yeah they're
geometrically part of a ho which is
bigger than either of them
yeah yeah you know I think if we want to
get in there we better get in I'm sorry
sorry
the proceeding program is copyrighted by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu